#我們家的那個
Our...I mean,
#那個竹鼠棚啊 現在都養滿啦
our bamboo rats shred is already full,
#都不夠放啦
and we have no more cells now.
#現在我們再租了一個廠房
We now have rented one more site.
#來把那個臼鼠規模啊 稍微養多一點
so that the scale of the bamboo rats....we can keep slightly more.
#就在這后面 我帶大家去看一下
It's just behind us. Let me take you to have a look.
#這一片都是 這邊也是
This whole area is ours, and this side too.
#這個過幾天就會拉走
These will be removed in a few days.
#這個 沙石
These are....sand and rocks.
#這邊也是
And here as well.
#這邊好多蘆葦啊
Here is a lot of reed.
#這一口池塘在這上面 (不明白怎麼池塘會在上面，所以照譯算了)
Above it is a pond.
#不知道有沒有魚
I wonder if there're any fish.
#下次拿抽水機過來抽一下
I'll come with my draining machine to drain away the water next time.
#你看 那裡都有山泉水流下來
Look! Spring water is flowing down from there too.
#看上去山泉水很大的水一樣哦 (甚麼是「很大的水」?)
It seems that the spring water is a very big water.
#就在這山頂上流下來哦
It's flowing down right from the peak.
#你看 這裡還有一個
Look! Here is also an,
#螞蟻窩
an ant lair.
#哎喲 你們該搬家啦
Ayo! You need to move away now!
#把它們
I will...
#窩搞散 等下它們自己會跑到另外一個地方做窩的
smash their lair and then they'll build a new one somewhere else.
#好多螞蟻呀
A lot of ants.
#好啦 不管他們
Well, I'll leave them alone.
#等下它們自己會搬家
They'll move away on their own.
#你看 這個還是前兩天做的
Look! These were just built a couple of days ago.
#嗯 現在我們做的這個池子啊
Um, the cells that we are now building,
#不像我們原來那個東倒西歪的
are not the shaky one like those we now have.
#現在都是拉了綫 (不知道怎麼拉甚麼線，反正就是量度了令其水平吧)
These are all leveled.
#你看 這個線都還是這裡
Look! The line is still here.
#它這樣就是很直的嘛 有線拉在這裡
It can be made very straight using this, by pulling a line from here.
#就這樣慢慢做 不趕時間的
Then we can build slowly as there is no hurry.
#做得很漂亮哦
Very pretty cells can be built!
#這個是繁殖池 這全部都是繁殖池哦
These are breeding cells, all these here are breeding cells.
#那邊就做商品 養商品的 (「商品鼠」是村霸私人號經常出現的名詞，可以建議一下更好翻譯，日後將其統一)
Those are merchandise, for merchandise rats.
#我們再去看一下其它地方
Let's take a look at other places.
#這裡還有做哦
Some cells are being built here too.
#這一邊 就這樣一過去應該有800平方左右
This side, it should be, should be around 800 square meters all the way.
#加上樓上800有1600 有1600平方
Together with 800 upstairs, it adds up to 1600 square meters.
#這裡空地的話1700多平方 朼將近3畝 3畝地
This empty space occupies more than 1700 square meters, which is almost 3 "mu", 3 "mu" of land. (1 "mu" = 666.666 square meters)
#到時這蘆葦呀 隨便搞一下搞一下 (那個「搞」想了很久也不知他想說甚麼，我當作「清理」算了)
Then the reed, we can just clear, clear that area
#種一點象草
and plant some elephant grass,
#種點像草就可以啦
some elephant grass, then it would be nice.
#嗯 我去樓上看一下
Um. Let me go upstairs to have a look.
#還上還有 也很 很大的哦 樓上
There is still, very, it's very large, upstairs.
#你看 這裡是住人的哦 都是一隔隔開的
Look! This is a residential area. It's divided into compartments.
#前面看一下 前面有點黑喲
Let me have a look there. It's a bit dark.
#還是鎖匙的
I need a key.
#哇 這還有間套房啊 (其實視頻顯示不是套房，但不理了，照譯)
Wa! Here is suite.
#這裡 還帶花的 不知道是誰的
Here, with the flowery pattern, whose' that?
#哇 這是好東西咬[SIC]喲
Wa! This is wonderful!
#下次我有空的時候來吃掉你
Next time when I have the time, I'll have a feast of you.
#黃蜂好大窩哇
Wasps. A big lair.
#哇 好像有那個黃鋒子啦 (甚麼是黃鋒子？)
Wa! It seems that there are...pupa.
#下次我要把它吃啦
I'll eat them next time.
#你看 這兩三個
Here, a couple of,
#腌 腌那個咸菜的缸哦 (口吃出現地方是句子開頭，所以保留位置，但字改變了)
jars, jars for pickled vegetables.
#到時候我們就有 咸菜吃啦
We can have, have pickles.
#哇 這好多房間啊
Wa! A lot of rooms.
#這個 這個
This one, this one
#這個是辦公室
This is an office.
#哇 還有兩張椅子在這裡
Wa! There are even two chairs.
#新的哦 這個椅子 就是有點髒 抺乾淨就行了
They are new, just a bit dirty. Should be fine after some cleaning.
#玻璃有點爛
The glass is a bit broken.
#哇 這是
Wa! This is
#這怎麼有根繩子
Why is here a string?
#這有根繩子哦
Here is a string.
#是不是誰在這裡睡過覺
Has somebody slept here?
#一根繩子睡覺
Slept on a piece of string.
#別摔跤哦
Don't fall.
#上面有個蕩千秋的綫就好啦
It would be nice if there were wires for up there. Then I could swing,
#沒事可以蕩一下千秋
when I have nothing to do.
#這個可以拿去 拿去 拿去家裡打板栗哦 這個
This can be taken to, to, to knock the chestnuts, I mean this rod.
#很乾了的 又很輕哦
It's very dry, and light.
#一個手都行
I can hold it by just one hand.
#等下我帶回去
Let me bring it back.
#打攝影小哥家的板栗
to knock the chestnuts at Mr. Cameraman's place.
#很結實啊
It's very firm.
#這兩根也是
Both of them.
#誒 有彈性
Ey! It's elastic.
#嗯
Um?
#誰家的鴨子
Whose duck is it?
#哇 這還有兩個池哦
Wa! Here are two little ponds too.
#也可以養魚
I can keep some fish too.
#養點魚出來
Keep some fish.
#放點蛇頭魚下去
Put some snakehead fish.
#邊是蓋起來 不蓋的話 煮魚湯一樣那麼熱
The edge needs to be covered. Otherwise, it would be as hot as making a soup,
#把魚都煮死啦
and the fish would be boiled to death.
#你看 這下面有3口魚塘哦
Look! Down there are three ponds.
#那個不知道甚麼東西動了一下
What's that? I just saw something moving.
#扔一個石頭下去
Let me throw a rock.
#沒反應
No response.
#下次我抽完水來抓
I'll catch it after draining out the water next time.
#那裡還有一個大水潭哦
There's another big pond.
#額 前兩天我還看了一下
Eh, I looked into it a couple of days ago.
#好多魚在那裡
There're a lot of fish.
#下次我們有空的時候就在那裡釣魚
Next time when we have the time, we can go fishing there.
#你看 魚竿都不用 魚竿都不用帶
Look! No rod, you don't even need a rod.
#上面就是竹子
Above the pond are bamboos.
#砍幾根竹子下來 就直接在那裡釣
We can chop some bamboo, and fish right there.
#現在是修路 上面是修了一點路
Now a road, a road is being paved over there.
#所以這個水就有點 有點髒髒的
So the water is quite, quite dirty.
#等下明天就很乾淨了的
But it will become very clean tomorrow.
#這條小河
This river,
#很漂亮的哦
is pretty.
#你看 我們村在修路哦
Look! A road is being paved in our village.
#從這裡一直
From here, all the way...
#從國道 這上面就是國道 一直修 修到我們家裡邊去
From the national highway, up there is the national highway, the road is paved, paved all the way to our village.
#這是打那個柏油路哦
This will be paved by tarmacadam
#兩車道的
with two lanes.
#到時候甚麼車都可以開得進來啦
Then all types of cars can come to our village.
#應該有6米 6米多寬
It should be 6 meters, more than 6 meters width
#兩車道的
with two lanes.
#應該下個月 下個月就可以修好
I think next month, it should be completed by next month.
#現在他的灑水車在那裡
Now the watering car is over there.
#修路的機器也放在那裡
The paving machines are over there.
#馬上就修好啦
It should be completed right away.
#好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
#我們要回家喂[SIC]竹鼠啦
We need to go back to feed the bamboo rats.